- [Instructor] useEffect is another React hook
that lets you apply side effects on every render
based on the latest props and a previous state.
useEffect takes two parameters,
a callback function and a list of dependencies.
This allows to apply side effects whenever there is a change
in the state within the components.
In our example, we want to verify
if the user input matches two values added together,
then apply side effects based on the results
based on whether the answer is right or wrong.
Back in Codespaces, I made some changes
and decided to include parts of the code into components
to make the code better organized into multiple components.
This is a key feature of the React library
which is called composition,
which is to divide and organize the UI into small units.
And you're going to see that inside the root components app.
We now have child components,
and now we share the state by passing data as props.
And based on the state changes,
we want to apply side effects.
So what we do, for example, is pass in this function
as a prop, and we pass this other function,
guessTheNumber, that we are yet to implement.
And we're going to use these functions
to add up these two random values together.
But first, we want to define another state variable,
and that's going to be results
and checkResults for the function.
And so the default value for this one will be zero.
So let's add up the two together.
That's going to be checkResults.
That's going to be values.random1 plus values.random2.
And so this result, we want to pass this
as a prop to this component result.
And this is inside this component result
that we want to apply side effects
based on the state of results.
So this one results.
We're going to use this P tag to display a message.
So so far for the game, what we do
is to generate two random numbers,
then we add up the two together.
Next, we want to compare the sum with the user input.
And finally, based on the results,
based on whether the answer is correct or not,
we want to display a success message or a fail message.
So we're going to do that with useEffect
to apply the side effects and display a message.
So we're going to define useEffect.
This one takes two parameters.
First, a callback function and a list of dependencies.
And it is inside the callback function
that you define the operations to apply the side effects.
And what we want is to display a message
based on the state, based on the results,
and in order to read the state, we need to add the prop.
This will be results and input.
And what we want is to compare the two,
and we're going to get an answer which will be correct or not.
And actually, I should name this one answer,
because we're going to then evaluate if this is correct or not.
So we're going to compare the two.
It's going to be result with input.
And because input is a text value, we want to make sure
that we wrap this one within this function, parseInt.
And next, what we want is to display the message.
So I'm going to define a new state variable,
local state variable.
That's going to be setMessage.
And by default, it's just going to be an empty string.
And based on the answer, we're going to evaluate the answer.
It's going to be true or false.
We're going to display a success message or a fail message.
It's going to be "You guessed right",
or "Try Again" if this is not correct.
So let's try that.
So first, you want to also be able
to display the corresponding message.
We're going to run the app,
so let's just make sure that this is up and running.
You're going to run with npm start.
Here we go.
So by default, you're going to read "You guessed right,"
and that's because we must also check something right here.
So inside, you see that right here
in the list of dependencies,
we are not specifying any state variable,
so we want to make sure that we are specifying here
because we want to be able to apply side effects
whenever there is a change in the states
that we read from the props.
And the other thing you want to check if there is any results.
So you want to check first
that we click on the button to check the results.
And in the case there is no results yet,
you just want to display an empty string,
because you want to display a message
only when we play the game.
So first what we do is to generate two numbers,
and purposely I'm just going to, you know.
So let's just run the app again.
So we're going to generate two numbers.
I'm going to add a number that I know is wrong, then check.
Then it's going to tell me that,
because this is wrong, try again.
I'm going to be again, and this time it's going to be easy.
So this one, it's going to be 21, and here we go.
So now I've got a correct answer
and so I can read, "You guessed right,"
which is a success message.
So now we've been able to successfully manage the state
between multiple components
by using useStates and useEffects.
And the application works based on the state
and not with instructions.
It is important to understand
what is declarative programming,
which is a high-level concept
that expresses the logic of a program
without specifying the control flow,
meaning that instead of describing
how a task should be performed step by step,
it focuses on describing the what and the desired outcome.
This is what we do in our example.
We run the program and manage the state with the hooks,
then we apply the side effects
based on the state passed to child components.
So we tell the program when to apply the side effects,
meaning that we apply the side effects
whenever there is a change in the states.
So now we see that the application is growing really fast.
We now manage and update multiple state variables
to keep track of random values and also the user inputs
and the results submitted by the user.
Finally, we display a win or a fail message.
So there is a lot of things going on.
When the app is growing along with the logic,
we need to keep things organized and tidy.
I thought this could be a good time
to introduce you to another hook, useReducer,
which is an alternative to useState
and perfect to handle complex logic.